

305 N. University St., Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN 47907

□ (+1) 765-409-0693 | ■ xinruw@purdue.edu | ★ https://xinruw.github.io/ | □ Xinru Wang | 🎓 Xinru Wang

Research Interest

My research lies at the intersection of human-computer interaction (**HCI**) and explainable AI (**XAI**). I utilize both experimental and computational approaches to explore **user-centered evaluation** of AI explanations in **AI-assisted decision making**, and finally seek to better design XAI systems that human users can interact with effectively.

Education

Purdue University West Lafayette, IN, US

Ph.D. in Computer Science, GPA: 3.93/4.00

Aug. 2019 - Present

· Advisor: Ming Yin

Peking University

Beijing, China

B.S. IN PSYCHOLOGY (DUAL DEGREE), GPA: 3.51/4.00 Sep. 2016 - Jun. 2019

Peking University

Beijing, China

B.S. IN INTELLIGENCE SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY, GPA: 3.65/4.00 Sep. 2015 - Jun. 2019

• Thesis: "Analysis of MOOC Forum Data towards Al Support" Thesis Advisor: Xiaoming Li

Professional Experience

Meta Reality Labs Redmond, WA, US

RESEARCH INTERN Sep. 2023 - Present

• Mentor: Anna Mengjie Yu

• Work on human interaction with explainable AI assistance on AR devices.

Megagon Labs

Mountain View, CA, US

RESEARCH INTERN May. 2023 - Aug. 2023

• Mentor: Hannah Kim, Zhengjie Miao

• Explored a Human-LLM collaborative annotation framework aimed at reducing cost and increasing efficiency. Submitted a paper to CHI 2024.

Purdue University West Lafayette, IN, US

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Aug. 2019 - Present

- Advisor: Ming Yin, Assistant Professor
- Conducted large-scale online human-subject experiments to evaluate how AI explanation impacts human decision-making processes.
- Proposed a space of three-component (i.e. inference + utility + selection) human behavior models in Al-assisted decision making.

University of Michigan Ann Arbor, MI, US

SUMMER RESEARCH INTERN

Jul. 2018 - Sep. 2018

- · Advisor: Lionel Robert, Professor
- · Investigated bi-directional trust in semi-autonomous vehicles through user testing, data extraction, and trust modeling.

Kendall Square Capital Beijing, China

Machine Learning Intern

Jan. 2019 - Apr. 2019

• Extracted time-series features from the limit order book data for prediction of mid-price movement in high frequency trading.

DiDiBeijing, China

Machine Learning Intern Sep. 2018 - Jan. 2019

• Implemented machine learning models to predict drivers' order-taken behavior and waiting-time on a million-scale database.

Publications

Human-LLM Collaborative Annotation

Xinru Wang, Hannah Kim, Sajjadur Rahman, Kushan Mitra, Zhengjie Miao. *In submission*

XINRU WANG · RÉSUMÉ

The Effects of AI Biases and Explanations on Human Decision Fairness: A Case Study of Bidding in Rental Housing Markets

Xinru Wang, Chen Liang, Ming Yin. IJCAI 2023

Who Should I Trust: AI or Myself? Leveraging Human and AI Correctness Likelihood to Promote Appropriate Trust in AI-Assisted Decision-Making

Shuai Ma, Ying Lei, Xinru Wang, Chengbo Zheng, Chuhan Shi, Ming Yin, Xiaojuan Ma. CHI 2023

Watch Out For Updates: Understanding the Effects of Model Explanation Updates in Al-Assisted Decision Making

Xinru Wang, Ming Yin. CHI 2023

Will You Accept the AI Recommendation? Predicting Human Behavior in AI-Assisted Decision Making

Xinru Wang, Zhuoran Lu, Ming Yin. WWW 2022

Effects of Explanations in Al-Assisted Decision Making: Principles and Comparisons

Xinru Wang, Ming Yin. ACM Transactions on Interactive Intelligent Systems (TiiS), 2022

Are Explanations Helpful? A Comparative Study of the Effects of Explanations in AI-Assisted Decision-Making

Xinru Wang, Ming Yin. IUI 2021

Patent_

Recommendation Method for Recipes Based on Deep Learning

Xinru Wang, Yichun Wang, Zhilou Yu. CN107665254A, Patent filed in Feb. 2018 (In Chinese)

Teaching

CS471 Introduction to Artificial Intelligence, Purdue University

Head Teaching AssistantFall 2022, Spring 2023Teaching AssistantFall 2019

CS242 Introduction to Data Science, Purdue University

Teaching Assistant Spring 2020

CS38001 Python Programming, Purdue University

Teaching Assistant Fall 2019, Spring 2020

Talk

Understanding Human Behavior in Al-Assisted Decision Making: Experiments and Models

Apr. 2022

MIDAS Future Leaders Summit 2022, University of Michigan

Professional Service

Program Committee

• CHI HCXAI workshop 2022 & 2023, FAccT 2023

Reviewer

• TiiS, CHI 2023, CHI 2023 Late-Breaking Work, CHI 2024

Student Volunteer

• SIGIR 2018

Honors & Awards _____

2023	Graduate Teaching Award , Purdue University Department of Computer Science	West Lafayette, IN, US
2018	Academic Excellence Award, Peking University (top 10%)	Beijing, China
2018	Fei-Xun Scholarship, Peking University	Beijing, China
2016	Academic Excellence Award, Peking University (top 15%)	Beijing, China
2016	May 4th Scholarship, Peking University	Beijing, China

Skills

Programming Python, R, HTML/CSS/JavaScript, SQL, MATLAB, C/C++, Java

Frameworks Pandas, Numpy, sklearn, PyTorch, Meteor **Languages** Chinese, English (GRE 162+170+3.5, TOEFL 111)